The traffic during this period,
这段时间的流速啊
is generally higher.
流量整个会比较高
Yesterday, due to the earthquake in Beijing,
昨天啊因为这个北京地震
I was really scared.
我这个非常害怕啊
I didn't get much sleep last night.
大半夜的没睡好啊
Hardly slept at all.
基本都没睡啊
I only managed to fall asleep when it was just getting light, around five.
五点多天都蒙蒙亮才睡
So I spent most of yesterday watching videos.
所以昨天看了半天视频
There was this one older guy,
其中有一位老大哥呢
who is a Ph.D. from Peking University.
他是一个北大的一个博士
I'm not sure what his specific field is,
具体干什么专业的
though.
不知道啊
He mentioned that he wants to become a knowledge creator.
然后他就说他想做知识博主
And every day
然后呢每天
he reads 150 pages of books every day
每天啊他看150页书
without fail
雷打不动
while others play games
别人打游戏
he focuses on reading
他就看书啊
others have top-notch computer setups
别人那个电脑配置好
the school gives him the worst one
学校给他配一个最破的
why does he read so much
为什么他要看书
apart from reading
他除了看书
He doesn't do anything at all. But he thinks he's so great. He's very proud of himself. And he said his kid came over to play with him. He does that too. Reading books. Without fail. He used to write doctoral dissertations for others.
他什么都不干啊 然后自己非常的了不起 他是很骄傲的啊 然后他说他孩子过来找他玩 他也是啊 看书啊 雷打不动 曾经给别人写博士论文
To earn some extra money.
赚点外快
So then
然后呢
but later it delayed my reading time
但是呢后来耽误自己看书了
so I have to read again
所以又要看书啊
got to read
看书啊
I don’t know how this guy is doing now
我不知道这位老哥现在混的怎么样
how many followers he has
粉丝量多少
but to be honest
但是我说实在的
because I feel like I still have something to say
因为我觉得我还有点发言权
since I’m in the knowledge category
因为我是知识类这赛道的嘛
And his high self-esteem
还有他这样的高自尊
A combination of high self-esteem and high education is particularly disastrous
人格是高自尊加高学历是特别完蛋的一种组合
Because a person spends too much time on their studies
因为一个人花了太多的时间在他的学业上
He must be very good at exams
他肯定是考试啊
And extremely knowledgeable
读书非常的厉害
But what's most important in society is making money
但是在这个社会上混最重要的就是把钱赚到手
Some people say
然有人说啊
Money isn't everything
钱不重要
In the end, I want to enjoy life
最后我就要享受人生了
He already has kids
他都有孩子了
Can you say money isn't important?
能说钱不重要吗
Right?
对不对
Having a family is a whole different ball game compared to not having one When you don’t have a family or aren’t married Without kids You can say that I do it for this hobby For the ideals, poetry, and distant dreams I go abroad to study every day
你有了家庭跟你没家庭的时候是两回事 你没家庭没结婚 没小孩的时候 你可以说啊 我就为了这个爱好 理想诗和远方 我天天出国留学啊
I travel abroad every day
天天出国玩儿啊
I can live and travel anywhere
我去哪儿地方旅居隐居都可以啊
Just like that guy who fights in the ring
就像那个打拳架格斗那个大哥似的
Isn't it that in the end, there's no money when Mom gets sick?
是不是最后老妈生病也没钱啊
Crying poor to net friends
跟网友哭穷
Finally, scraping together some money
最后凑点钱
Then going back to full armor fighting
然后又去打全甲去了啊
Many such men have high self-esteem
很多这种男人就是自尊心又高
Actually, it means you haven’t figured yourself out.
实际上是没把自己琢磨明白
If a person is poor,
一个人如果穷的话
and has a high sense of self-respect,
自尊心又高
that can be a really tough situation.
那真的是非常要命的事
Especially for those with high education.
特别是学历高的人
People with high education,
学历高的人
don’t assume that
你不要以为
having a high education means you’re highly capable,
你学历高就代表你能力高
or that you understand society very well.
就代表你非常了解这个社会
Because, ultimately, society values your ability to earn money.
因为这个社会最终看重的就是你的挣钱能力嗯
The ability to earn money is truly important.
挣钱能力真的很重要啊
But the real money is what you actually earn.
而真挣到钱的是钱
Figuring out how to do this takes time.
你对这种东西的摸索
It’s a long process. Interpersonal skills and reading people are crucial. These are things you need to learn. You have to take a business approach. And you need to be able to estimate prices. To assess this trend
这个是要花很长时间的啊 接人待物啊啊察言观色 这都得学 要走着做生意路线啊 估价呀 判断这个流行趋势啊
To gauge the demand
判断需求啊
It's all the same
都是得那样的
Including what I've been telling everyone for a long time
包括我跟大家说了很长时间啊
When you're in business
做生意的
At the beginning, it might be about curbing your spending urges
刚一开始可能就是要限制你的消费欲望
To save money
要攒钱
To keep your finances in check
让你在财政上要比较那什么
And I'm not sure if it's humility or something else
还有我不知道是谦虚还是怎么着
Anyway, the money earned isn't particularly high.
反正赚的钱不是特别多啊
The personal funds are quite limited.
自有的资金特别少一点
Of course, it might be because of the PhD.
当然可能因为是博士
When it comes to housing, though,
所以在住房上面来讲的话
the benefits from the school might be a bit better.
再加上学校待遇方面来讲可能会好一些
But apart from the PhDs I know,
但是我身边这些博士以外
most people are living quite modestly.
大部分都是很过得很贫苦的
But to be honest with you,
但是我跟你说实在的
I feel like, apart from one or two people,
就是我感觉我身边除了一两个啊
He's truly a very successful doctor in the business world.
真的是在这个商业上非常成功的博士啊
Unexpectedly.
额以外
The rest of these doctors are typically highly educated.
剩下的这些博士们通常都是高学历
And they earn a modest income.
然后赚一点点钱
Yet, they have exceptionally strong egos. You can see he just can't accept this reality. So his stress will keep piling up. Because many of his aspirations for reality Are quite idealistic. I often say that idealism can be fatal.
然后特别的自尊心非常的强 你看他就接受不了这种现实 所以他压力会越来越大 因为他对现实当中的很多憧憬 是比较理想化的啊 我常常说理想主义害死人
Especially when you hit your thirties or forties.
就是你一旦到这个三四十岁了
If your expectations of society remain idealistic,
如果你对社会的预期仍然是比较理想主义的话
it means you're not well-prepared for the practical aspects of living in it,
那就是说你对于社会生存方面
especially when it comes to starting a family.
特别是建立家庭方面
You'll find yourself struggling to make ends meet.
你就会比较捉襟见肘啊
Many people simply can't adapt to society.
很多人其实就是不适应社会啊
It's not that they can't adapt to the world as it is,
不能说不适应世俗
but they think making money is degrading.
而是这些东西他认为挣钱非常的丢人啊
Thinking about these things is really quite base.
想这些事非常的低级啊
One should have people fawning over them.
自己就应该有人舔着
People groveling.
有人哈着
People carrying them in a sedan chair.
有人抬着轿子
He feels quite pleased with himself.
他觉得他还很高兴啊
That's not the case.
不是这样的
Most importantly, when it comes to being a person,
做人最重要的来讲
It's crucial to meet others' expectations of you.
就是要符合他人对你的预期啊
These expectations can be seen as a kind of demand.
这种预期来讲可以说是一种诉求
It can also be referred to as demand.
也可以说是需求
For example, the expectations people have of me.
比如说大家对我的预期
They hope I talk about topics that I find interesting.
希望我讲一些自己感兴趣的话题
So I need to pay attention to what topics people are into. What they are interested in. I’ll talk about those topics. If I don’t understand those topics. Then I need to read up on them. I need to do some research. Is that right? If I read 150 pages a day
所以我就要关注大家到底什么样的话题 感兴趣啊 我去说这类话题 说这类话题我不懂 那我就要去看书 我要去研究 对不对 如果我一天啊看150页书
it's a fixed quantity, you see
是一个定量的东西来讲
it's like telling yourself
其实这就跟自己说啊
I need to review for 300 days
我要复习300天
I need to get into Peking University
我要考上北大一样
of course, he has already been admitted to Peking University
当然他啊已经考上北大了
his life has been relatively smooth
他这个人生就是容易很多的时候吧
it's easy to develop a path dependency
就容易产生路径依赖
Once you believe you've succeeded at something
就是你一旦认为你做什么东西成了
you tend to keep pushing yourself
你就容易不停地去要求自己
to be disciplined
就是自律
which leads to success
通向的是成功嘛
Many people don't understand this
很多人不明白这一点
when it comes to touching yourself or touching others
就是在感动自己跟感动他人之间
who should you choose to touch
到底应该选择感动谁
You should choose to touch others
你应该选择的是感动他人
rather than yourself
而不是感动你自己
You have to deceive yourself.
自己要进行欺骗啊
Intense self-deception.
高强度的自我欺骗
Only by fooling yourself can you
你只有骗得过自己以后
break free from your emotional traps.
你才能从自己的情绪陷阱当中啊挣脱出来
As long as your emotions are right,
只要你的情绪是对的
your physical state is right,
你的体力是对的
then you’ll find that everything you do will be much more efficient. Some people watch me record videos while eating. He gets particularly impatient. This impatience of yours. You need to understand the reason behind this impatience.
嗯这时候你做任何事情都会事半功倍啊 有人就是看我一边录视频 一边吃东西 他就会特别的耐不耐烦啊 你这种不耐烦 你要明白这种不耐烦的原因是何在
It's not because you think my video is too slow.
不是因为你看我的视频觉得慢了
It's because you feel disrespected.
而是你觉得是一种不尊重
This feeling of disrespect comes from.
而这种不尊重的感觉来自于
Your belief that you deserve respect.
你觉得你应该受到尊重
Do you really believe you deserve respect?
你觉得你真的应该受到尊重吗
What have you done to earn respect from others?
你做了什么需要得到别人的尊重
Why can't you get things done when others don't respect you?
你为什么别人不尊重你
Is it because you can't function without respect?
你就做不了事情
What is the essence of respect?
尊重的核心到底是什么
Is it equality?
是平等吗
Or is it about having a certain status?
还是你心中有一个地位
Is it about a hierarchical relationship?
有一个主从的关系
Is it about a seniority-based respect?
有一个尊卑的长幼的关系
Is it about order?
有一个次序
Is it about some feudal concept?
有一个封建上面一个东西
So you can't stand seeing others living freely.
所以你看不得别人自由自在啊
This is the core issue with this person.
这就是这个人的核心的问题
He wants to make money, you see.
就是他心中又想啊赚到钱
He wants to have paternal authority,
要想有父权
and marital authority,
又想有夫权
and the power to dominate others.
又想有凌驾于他人之上的这种权利
And others have to cater to him.
那别人又得哈着他
So this kind of person is actually the easiest to deal with. That's the intelligentsia. Especially, the high-ranking intelligentsia are the easiest to deal with. That's why I say many PhDs and such. In terms of personal conduct, one still needs to be particularly cautious. If you are studying sociology,
所以这种人其实是最好对付的 就是知识分子 特别是高级知识分子是最好对付的 所以我说很多博士啊之类的 在做人这方面其实还是需要特别啊 如果你是研究社会学
historiography,
历史学的
or any of the humanities,
你是做人文学科之类的
these PhDs might be more adept in this aspect.
这些博士可能会啊这方面会比较游刃有余一点
Those from Shanke,
山科的
might pay a bit more attention.
可能会注意一点
But many people struggle with interpersonal skills
但是很多人在做人这方面
when it comes to maintaining these social relations
在维持这种社会关系这方面来讲并不行啊
making money ultimately comes down to one thing
赚到钱其实唯独就是一件事
meeting others' needs
就是满足别人的需求
the process of fulfilling these needs can involve providing a service
这种需求被满足的过程可以是提供服务
the more frequently you provide this service
提供服务的这个频次越高啊
the higher your chances of earning more
你赚到的钱的几率就越高
it's that simple
就这么简单
if we look at it from a knowledge perspective
如果从知识的角度来讲
So from the perspective of knowledge,
所以从知识的角度来讲
you need to offer a service to others,
你要提供别人一种服务
which means you need to have a service mindset,
就得有一种服务意识
you need to make people happy,
就得让别人高兴
providing emotional value is essential,
情绪价值是一定要提供的
you need to make different people feel good,
你让不同的人情绪高兴
which means you have to categorize them into at least 25 personality types, for different personality types, you should know how to handle them. People come from different backgrounds How you should act like the intelligentsia Especially, high-ranking intellectuals are quite easy to handle
你就必须要把他能分成至少25种人格来啊 不同的人格的人 你应该什么样的方法对付他 不同的人的出身 你应该怎样像知识分子 特别是高级知识分子很好对付
Very easy indeed
非常好对付啊
Almost like a textbook
基本上就像教科书一样
You just need to verify their origins
你只要证明他来路啊
Make sure it’s not easy to do so
不容易就可以了
Taking care of their self-esteem is enough
照顾好他的自尊心就可以了啊
Then, you need to do it in front of them
然后要他在他的面前
You come across as very humble
你显得很谦卑
showing a great deal of respect to him
显得非常重视他啊
constantly flattering him
不停的拍他的马屁
even though he might put up various pretenses
虽然他会各种各样的让
he actually enjoys the process immensely
但是他呢会非常的享受这个过程
because people like him are often overlooked by society
因为这类人通常是不太被社会
and not frequently noticed by the general public
大众所经常会注意到的
so for someone who is not easily noticed
所以像这种不太容易被注意到的人
giving them excessive attention
你给他过分的注意哈
Even if it's fake, giving him too much of this kind of need
给他过多的这种哪怕是假的这种需求
He will satisfy those psychological needs
心理上的需求他都会满足
So if someone is in the high-end service industry
所以一个人他如果做的是高端服务业
They must consider everyone's preferences
就必须要考虑到每个人的喜好
Different personalities
不同性格的人
At least what the majority of personalities are like
起码多数人的性格是什么样
If you don't Distinguish between people Categorize people Different people have different strategies, you won't be able to adapt to society. So for many people,
如果你不进行 打人进行区分 把人进行归类 不同的人有不同的策略的话 你就没有办法适应这个社会 所以很多人来讲的话
they've spent enough time in the ivory tower at home,
他在象牙塔家里待的时间够长了
the longer the time,
时间越长
the more they are surrounded by similar people,
周围也都是这样的人
there are no other examples to refer to.
没有其他的样本可以参考啊
So often,
所以很多的时候来讲
why some people who stay in academia for too long
为什么有些人在学术界待久了以后
You need to readjust to the civil service examination.
考公还要重新适应
Entering society,
走向社会
he needs to readjust as well.
他要重新适应
So often,
所以很多的时候
don't think that you're competing in a fierce battle just to cross a narrow bridge.
你不要看说你千军万马挤独木桥
Once you make it through,
你过去了
I got into a 985 or 211 university,
我上了985211
and then I landed a job at a major company.
然我进了大厂啊
I went through the selection process.
我进行了选调
You would be perfect
你就一定完美了
No, that's not true
不是的
Life isn't just a series of battle royale games
你不是人生都是一些吃鸡游戏
In many cases
很多的时候来讲的话
People are often eliminated early on
人所谓的早被筛出去啊
Ordinary girls are often out of the running by their mid-teens
平民公主十三四十四五的时候就被筛出去
Even when they face society
就算面向社会了
Others start dating in their mid-twenties
人家二十五六的时候谈恋爱
Dating experience is essentially experience in dealing with the opposite sex
谈恋爱经验就是对付异性的经验
It's just richer than you
就是比你丰富
There's nothing we can do about it
那没有办法
So in many cases
所以很多的时候来讲
It's not about thinking you're the apple of the world's eye
不是在于你认为你自己是天之骄子
The world truly recognizes you You are the apple of the world's eye To put it bluntly, if you can't make money You're a failure Not being able to make money definitely makes you a failure Earning money, in itself, is about accumulating material wealth. It’s better for you as a male,
世界社会真正认可你 你是天之骄子 说白了你挣不到钱 你就是废物啊 挣不到钱绝对是废物 因为挣钱的本身来讲是物质财富的积累 你作为一个雄性还好
or better for you as a female,
还是还是说你作为一个雌性还好
the process of building a family,
你建立家庭的过程
the process of raising offspring, all require a foundation of material wealth.
你繁育后代的过程都是需要物质财富基础啊
It’s not just about your personal consumption.
不是说光你自己去消费的
Your own consumption,
你自己去消费
you can live frugally,
你可以破衣拉撒
you can go without fancy clothes.
你可以不穿
You can go without makeup
可以不化妆
You can do nothing at all
可以什么都不弄
Can I bring my child?
带着孩子可以吗
Can a child go hungry?
孩子能饿着吗
Can a child go without changing their diaper?
孩子能纸尿裤不换吗
Can a child skip school?
啊孩子能不上学吗
Can a child skip medical appointments?
孩子能不看病吗
That's impossible
不可能
So when you belittle the foundation of material wealth
所以你贬低物质财富基础的时候
Often, it's because
那很多的时候来讲
you have nothing at all
就是因为你什么都没有
and in highly educated families like these
而且像这样的高知的这种家庭来讲
it's particularly easy to produce individuals with severely distorted personalities
特别容易会诞生出那种人格非常扭曲的人
why are children from teachers' families so often like that
为什么说教师的家庭的孩子呢都特别那什么
because children from teachers' families are often this way
因为教师家庭的孩子很多时候就是这样
their income and social status
收入与他的社会地位
are not proportional to their need for social respect
跟他的社会自尊心需求不成正比
because the money you earn doesn't bring you the respect you crave
因为你赚的钱得不到你要的尊重啊
It's that simple. So what many people truly need is respect, it's about respect. Money is dignity. a form of dignity. When you don't have money, if you still talk to me in a domineering way,
就这么简单 所以很多人需要的真正是什么 是respect 是尊重啊 钱就是尊严 是尊严的一种 你没有钱的时候来讲的话 你还要跟我吆五喝六的话
I'm definitely going to be unfriendly to you.
我肯定对你态度不好啊
When you have money
你有钱的时候
you treat me a bit worse
你对我态度差一点
I can still accept it
我也能接受
That's human nature
这就是人
So many times
所以很多的时候
we say you should read 150 pages in a day or so
我们说你去一天去看150页书也好
That's your own requirement
这是你对你自己的需求
You get yourself all worked up
你自己把自己感动的跟王八蛋似的
But it's actually of no use at all
实际上一点用都没有
Are you adapting to this society?
你适应这个社会吗
You're still earning a few thousand bucks
你还是挣几千块钱
and you have to support your family
然后还要养家
Are you getting used to this society?
你适应这社会吗
Even if you earn 10,000 bucks, so what?
就算你挣了1万块钱又怎样
When it comes to a place like Beijing
在北京这个地界来讲的话
you're still pretty much nobody
你其实还是什么都不是
So for me
所以对于我来讲的话
I think the realization of one's value
我觉得人的这种价值的发挥
The most important thing is to provide shelter and protection for the other family members.
最重要的就是啊为家庭其他的成员遮风挡雨
To earn enough money.
能赚到足够多的钱
On the track of power, wealth, and prestige,
在权力财富声望的赛道上呢
Try to move a bit further ahead.
尽量往前的走一点
Try to push a bit more.
尽量赶一点啊
If one generation moves forward a bit, they won’t be at a disadvantage.
一代人往前赶上一点就不吃亏
Then you can leverage the entire family’s strength.
然后你再利用你家族的整个力量
As the first generation to enter the city,
你作为第一代进入城市的第一代啊
Entering a new city.
进入一个新城市
When entering a new field,
一个新领域的话
if you don't expand your family's influence, the pressure on your children will be immense. That's why they say, 'Prosperity comes from serving as an official', and 'Weakness leads to commerce'. That's how it is. I told you, prosperity comes from serving as an official, but you won't listen.
你又不去扩大自己的家族 那你的孩子的压力就会非常大 所以所谓的富强做侍郎 母弱出商贾 就是这样啊 跟你说了 富强做侍郎 你又不听
You insist on taking the civil service exam
你非要去考公
Are you aiming to become an official?
你考的那是官吗
You’re a clerk
你是吏啊
You’re a low-ranking clerk
你是小吏
You’re a military captain
你是武都头啊
You’re not Gao Qiu
你不是高俅
So many times, it’s not about what you can do
所以很多的时候不是你能够怎么样呢
By leveraging your strengths
通过一己之长
And then somehow leaving others behind
然后怎么怎么着就把别人甩了之后了
You never thought about being squeezed off the narrow bridge
你从来就没有想到挤下独木桥
whether those people really fell down
那些人是不是真的掉了下去
So, as a diligent student from a small town
所以你作为一个小镇做题家
as the top learner in your county
作为一个县城里边学习最好的孩子
you made your way to a big city through hard work
你通过刻苦努力走到了大城市
and then you'd find yourself in an even larger and more confusing cycle
然后你就会进入更大的迷茫的怪圈
because you realize there are so many things
因为你发现这些东西好多东西
various resources
一些资源
advantageous resources
一些优势的资源
You can't get it.
你拿不到啊
You won't be able to access the advantageous resources.
优势资源拿不到
Earning money will be extremely difficult for you.
你挣钱就会非常难
You'll find that what you know
你发现自己懂得那些东西
is still less compared to children from urban areas.
相对于城市间的孩子来讲还是少
So you must catch up in sociology.
所以在社会学这方面你就必须补课
You have to show respect to others.
必须礼贤下士
Humbly accept opinions that differ from yours.
虚心的接受跟你不一样的意见
Especially as you get older. One has already taken a wrong turn. Wanting to come back is quite difficult. So, when it comes to relationships between people, high self-esteem and high education can be a very critical issue. High self-esteem,
你特别是岁数大了以后 人已经走岔了路了 想搬回来 那是很难的 所以说人之间的这种东西啊 高自尊高学历是非常要命的一件事情 高自尊啊
when paired with high education,
面面对着高学历来讲
they are two things that can coexist without contradiction.
他是一个并行不悖的一个东西
The stronger a person's self-esteem,
一个人的自尊心越强
The more he can't hear others' opinions, right?
他越听不见别人的意见是吧
The stronger a person's self-esteem is,
一个人自尊心越强
What he is like now,
他自己现在是什么样
What a jerk.
那是什么王八蛋
Just a jerk.
就是什么王八蛋
He will never change his ways.
一辈子也不会有改变
That's just how people are.
所以人就是这样
There are plenty of things you can't stand.
你受不了的事情多了
Can you stop me from eating ice cream?
你能不让我吃冰激凌吗
It's not just about being happy.
不可能我开心就可以
But the question is, are you happy now?
但问题是你现在开心吗
You're not happy right now.
你现在不开心
You still have to endure some systemic exploitation.
你仍然要忍受一些系统性的压榨啊
Some things established by usage in society.
一些社会上一些约定俗成的东西啊
You've entered the academic circle.
你进入了学术圈
There are certain rules you have to follow.
有些东西的规则你就得遵守
So do you think staying in that position will definitely be comfortable?
所以你觉得待着下卡在那里就一定舒服吗
Is getting a government job definitely going to be great?
考上了公家饭就一定爽吗
Is it really the case that entering a large company means you're set for life?
啊进入了大企业就一定就一定享受了人生嘛
Not at all.
都不是的
So, from the perspective of comfort, let me tell you, starting a business is tough in the beginning, but once you get on the right track, this cycle begins, and basically, you don't have to struggle as much anymore.
所以我从这个舒适的角度来讲 跟你们说 创业来讲就是刚一开始难 但是一旦你走上了路了以后 这种循环的模式开始了 基本上就不用你再费劲了
So, in reality, it's just a couple of hard years.
所以实际上就是辛苦两三年啊
A lifetime of happiness
幸福一辈子
But some people just won't listen
但有些人就是不听啊
The probability of failure in entrepreneurship is 99%
创业失业概率99%
So you're just going to stick around for your meager pension
那你就为了拿你那点公积金
Wasting your life in a government job, right?
在公家耗一辈子吧对吧
Wasting your life at a university
在大学里耗一辈子啊
Or in some research institute
在你的什么研究所里啊
Or something like that
或者怎么样
Of course, you definitely will
当然来讲你肯定啊
Some people come here
有些人来讲
specifically for scientific research
他专门搞科研的
to serve the country
报效祖国
and there's nothing wrong with that
这个没有问题
but the issue is, many people consider these institutes
但问题很多人他考虑这些院所
not just for the money
他不是他就是为了多拿点钱
if you're working for the money
你要是为了钱而工作的话
shouldn't you be more straightforward about your desires?
你不应该更加直白的面对自己的欲望吗
Right?
对不对
Money represents a relationship of free trade.
钱代表的就是一种自由的买卖的关系啊
With money, you have more time to manage your own schedule.
你有了钱有更多的时间来支配自己的时间
Life,
人生啊
you have more choices.
你可以有更多的选择啊
Of course, when you have choices,
当然来讲有选择的情况下
you might not necessarily spend it.
可能你也不会进行消费啊
Of course, some people find joy in spending. So, no worries. That's what I want to share with everyone. If your current situation isn't good the stronger your self-esteem is the more you'll struggle it might be better to have a bit less pride
当然有些人的生活的乐趣就是消费 所以没关系 所以我就跟大家说 如果你的现实境遇不好 你的自尊心越强 你就越倒霉啊 还不如自尊心低一点
follow Brother Rong
跟着荣哥啊
why not take a step forward
是不是往前走一走啊
and gain a new perspective
重新获得一下认知
once you've gained new insights
等你获得了新的认知以后
then you can move forward with confidence
你再吊一吊
It doesn't matter
那无所谓
Right?
对不对
You can look down on me again
你再瞧不起我
It's fine
没关系
After you get used to the original work
你看惯了原著以后
After you see what books I've read
你看过我看过什么书以后
You can look down on me again
你再瞧不起我
That's perfectly fine
你这样是可以的
Because by then you'll be above me
因为这时候你已经高过我了
You have no idea about the things I know.
你根本就不知道我知道的这些东西
Then you look down on me.
然后你就瞧不起我
Then you block me.
然后你就啊拉黑了啊
Labeling me as someone who spreads false doctrines.
就说这个人就是歪理邪说之类的
This has cast a shadow over your own life.
那你对你自己的人生就是产生了
How should I put it?
怎么说呢
The fog effect doesn't mean I'm in the fog.
迷雾效应不是我在迷雾当中啊
I've already walked out of the mist.
我已从雾中走出来了啊
I've found my own path.
我已经找到了自己的路
Found your location
找到了自己所在的位置
You don’t have it
你没有啊
So that’s how it is
所以这个东西就是这样
So who is currently in the mud
所以谁现在谁在泥潭当中
Who should be worried
谁应该着急
Your children read 150 pages every day Do you think you can become a knowledge influencer in the future Why don’t you give it a try See if your follower count will grow This is just a case of being proven wrong. If you have a large number of followers, then what I said would all be a waste of time.
儿女这样每天读150页书 你觉得你将来就能做知识博主了 那你就做做看啊 看看你的粉丝量会不会多 这就是一个打脸的事了 你要粉丝量多 我说的那些就全是浪费时间
If your follower count isn't high enough,
你要粉丝量不够多
then what you're doing is just a waste of time.
那你所做的事情那就是来浪费时间
So, to put it simply,
所以来讲
sometimes that's just how people are.
有时候人与人之间就是这样
You might have the key to how others should proceed,
你也许掌握着别人应该怎么干的
a crucial key.
一个关键性的钥匙
And people often don't know what to do.
而人通常不知道自己到底应该怎么办
Like me,
你像我
I often wonder when my followers will reach a million.
我经常想粉丝什么时候才能涨到100万啊
Do I need to start doing something more creative?
我是不是得抽象得整活啊
Should I start making short dramas?
得拍短剧啊
Or something like that.
得那什么
But later, I realized it's not like that.
后来我想其实不是这样的
Perhaps that's just the way life is.
也许人的命运就是如此啊
It's the cumulative effect of one period after another.
一段时间一段时间的啊综合的作用
So don't belittle the effort you're putting in now.
所以不要去贬低你现在所做的努力
And what you're doing is valuable to others,
而且你所做的东西他对其他人来讲
It's not about how much money you make,
不是说你赚多少钱
or how many followers you gain.
涨多少粉丝的问题
It's about whether what you do is useful to others.
而是你做这些东西对别人来讲有没有用
If more people get stuck,
更多的人如果卡壳
given the current situation,
在现在这个状态来讲
you need to figure out a way
你就必须要想办法
to steer them in the right direction. It's insurmountable So there's a great responsibility involved So in many cases Some of my content is specifically for my followers Specifically for them to listen to And for those who aren't followers
把这些人的这个方向给他调整过来 迈不过去 所以这就是一个伟大的责任在里边 所以很多的时候来讲 我的一些东西是专门给我的粉丝讲的 专门给他们去听的啊 而对于一些不是粉丝的人来讲
It might not be very useful
可能就没有什么用
So adjusting one's self-esteem is particularly important
所以调整自尊心的状态特别的重要
Look, self-esteem and such
你看自尊心这些东西
I've actually talked about this in countless episodes.
我其实说过无数期了
I think I need to bring it up from time to time.
我觉得我时不时的我就得拿出来说一说啊
Feeling moved by yourself is useless.
感动自己没有用
It’s no good even if you feel moved to tears.
感动自己感动的跟王八蛋的时候也没有用啊
Facing the reality of society,
面对社会的现实
you must always consider what others are thinking.
你一定要琢磨别人在想什么
What their needs are.
别人的需求是什么
Everything should be centered around others.
一切以别人为中心
You can't be too self-centered when dealing with people.
不能你做人可以自我一些
It's okay to be a bit narcissistic
可以自恋一些啊
It's okay to be a bit
可以自一些
a bit more confident is fine
自信一些都没关系
This is when you're adjusting your work state
这是你在调整自己的工作状态的时候
But when you're working on a product
但是你在做一个产品
or a service
做一个服务啊
when you're facing the public
在面向大众的时候
when you're addressing students
在面向学生
or an audience
面向观众
Facing
面
Facing your followers
面向你的粉丝
When facing your cinephiles
面向你的影迷的时候
It’s crucial to understand what they need
一定要明白大家需要的是什么
Because we are in the high-end public service industry
因为我们干的是高端的公众服务业啊
Communication studies has this characteristic
传播学就有这样的特点
If you’re hungry and don’t know to eat Thirsty and don’t know to drink You will die Right or wrong So at this point, what do you need now? What you need now is the support and recognition of the public. You need to create more resources that the public will enjoy.
如果你饿了不知道吃东西 渴了不知道喝水 你就会死亡 对不对 所以这个时候你现在需要的是什么 你现在需要的是大众的支持与认可 你就需要去产生出更多大众喜欢的资源
Just reading books on your own
一味的自己看书
You wouldn't know exactly which books to read.
你也不知道到底该看什么书
Like me, I often read books on business management.
你像我经常有时候看商学的书
I've been reading for a long time.
看了很长时间
Because my interest lies there.
因为我的兴趣在哪儿
I tend to read for extended periods during critical times
我就会关键时刻去读很长时间的书
Sometimes I would isolate myself
我有时候会闭关起来
And spend ten to twenty days completing a 100,000-word book
然后花十天20天把一本10万字的书写完
Right?
对不对
Sometimes it might only take six or seven days to finish
有时候可能就六七天就能写完
The question is whether I need to
问题就是我需要不需要
It's not about being persistent to achieve something
而不是说要持之以恒就能怎么样
You haven't even started your journey
你的路都没走
All at once
通过一次
How can you be so sure about reading 150 pages?
你怎么就能知道读150页书啊
Persist for a few years and you’re bound to succeed.
坚持几年就一定能成功呢
Now, apart from your kids,
你现在把除了孩子
You’ve been neglecting your family.
你忽视了家庭
And you haven’t earned much money either.
你忽视了钱也没挣多少
But your self-esteem has gone up.
自己自尊心倒上去了啊
You feel pretty good about yourself.
自己感觉挺好
What about my life?
我这辈子怎么样
I tell everyone how many books I’ve read in my life.
逢人就说我这辈子读了多少多少书
What’s the point? I graduated from a prestigious university.
有什么用呢啊我是名校毕业啊
I was the top scorer in the college entrance exam when I was young.
我年轻时候高考状元
How about me?
我怎么样
Have you seen Lei Jun mention his top exam score?
你看雷军提他高考状元这事了吗
I don’t think so. Right? Because you don’t have anything new. You don’t have any new achievements to boast about. That’s why you keep reminiscing about the old days. Back in the day, how things were Back in the day, I was the campus queen, yeah
没有吧 对不对 因为你没有新的 你没有新的成就可以炫耀 所以你才老想当年怎么怎么样 想当年怎么样 想当年我是校花嗯
Back in the day, your family was well-off, right?
想当年你们家阔过对吧
During the Qing Dynasty
大清的时候
What's the point of talking about those things?
说那些东西有什么用啊
Don't you feel embarrassed?
不觉得丢人吗
So, a lot of the time, when we talk about being a person
所以很多的时候我们说做人啊
Looking quite old
看着岁数很大
Many people, in fact, never really grow up
很多人其实就没长大
Many people's minds are still quite immature.
很多人的心智还是很幼稚啊
His belongings.
他的东西
His resilience.
他的承受力
The degree of distortion in his mind has become quite severe.
他心中那个扭曲的程度已经很强了
So as he got a bit older,
所以呢人大了一点呢
he wouldn’t listen to advice.
又不听劝啊
Actually, he’s almost 40 years old.
其实呢马上就40岁了
And then at 50,
然后在50岁
and again at 60.
然后再60岁
Then you'll be completely phased out by society.
然后你就被社会彻底淘汰了
So the most crucial thing is to stay aligned with the channels of social development.
所以最重要的是紧跟社会的发展的渠道
Look at what the mainstream population needs now.
看看现在社会的主流人群需要的是什么
What you offer must be relevant to the mainstream audience.
你提供的东西必须要跟主流人群过相关才行
It shouldn't be overly specialized content.
不应该是非常专业的东西
It should have a certain universal appeal. Something within the general public's interest that's worth sharing. Like the videos that went viral on Douyin for me, Mostly they have some topical elements to them. Things that are related to this viewer
是应该有一定普世性质的 有一定大众范围之内值得传播的东西 你像我在抖音上火的那些视频 基本上来讲都是有一些话题性的东西啊 跟这个观众有关系的东西
Things that align with the viewer's interests
跟观众的兴趣有关的东西
Things that meet the viewer's needs
跟观众的需求有关的东西
You need to have the audience in mind
就是心中你要有观众
If you're creating a show
如果你做的是节目
If you acknowledge that what you're creating is a product
如果你做的你承认你做的是节目是一种产品
The consumer is the one paying
那消费者买单
What the consumer likes and such
消费者喜欢什么之类的
You can't tell what they truly need from their comments
你不能从他的评论当中看出来他真正需要什么
You need to start by digging in
你要先去挖掘
You should give it a try
要尝试
When your self-esteem is very strong
当你的自尊心非常强的时候
This is where many UPloaders fall short, not even reaching half of what I do
这是很多up主不如我的一半了地方
They haven’t really thought about it
他们就没有琢磨过
Oh, like Rongzheng, he can just open his mouth and speak
哎呀你像荣政这人张口就能说呀
And then there’s the one who dresses in tattered clothes, you know what kind of image that is
然后那个穿的破衣拉撒的知道那是什么形象啊
Coming out without any makeup
不化妆就出来啊
Not even memorizing their lines
也不背稿
He didn't even have a teleprompter.
也没看他有提词器
But he still dared to speak like that.
他就敢那么说啊
What if he got it wrong?
万一说错了怎么办
He doesn't even separate his friend circles.
朋友圈也不分组
The things you don't understand are actually my strengths. The more I talk, the better I know what people like to hear. Naturally, I know what everyone likes to listen to. The more I practice, the better I get. I check the view count. I look at the audience trends I check the bounce rate
你所不理解的这些东西正是我优势的地方 我说的多了 自然知道大家喜欢听什么 我练的多了 我看播放量 我看观众的趋势 我看跳出率
I look at the completion rate
我看完播率
I naturally know what everyone really wants
我自然就知道大家到底想要的是什么
I don’t use scripts
我不用稿子
So I don’t have to write copy
所以我就不用写文案
Writing copy and then doing it
写文案再一弄
You might update once a week or once a month
你这样一个星期一个月更一期
I update seven times a week
我他妈一星期更七期
Episode 14
14期
Can you match me?
你拼得过我吗
You can't even match my combat experience, no matter how many times more you have.
你也拼不过我的作战经验就是你多多少倍
And the most important thing is that I don't care about face.
而且最重要的就是我不好面子
Chinese people care a lot about face.
中国人都好面子
I don't care about face.
我不好面子
In this aspect, I will be stronger than anyone else.
在这一点上我就会比所有人都强
Because my cost of trying is low.
因为我的尝试成本就低
So you must have something that makes you stronger than others.
所以你一定得有些东西强过别人
You might be able to stand your ground in the world.
你才可能在江湖上立足啊
You can't even handle throwing weapons.
你什么东西暗器也不行
Your lightness kung fu is no good either.
轻功也不行
Neither is your hard qigong.
硬气功也不行
Walking on walls and leaping over eaves is beyond you too.
飞檐走壁也不行
You can't wield swords or knives.
刀剑也不行
Not even guns or cannons are your forte.
枪炮也不行
You're no good at anything.
你什么都不行
Then what makes you think you can survive in this world?
那你又凭什么在江湖中立足呢
Right?
对不对
So when you talk a lot, there are some things you should listen to.
所以你跟你说很多的时候有些话要听啊
Especially when I often share practical advice.
特别像我经常讲干货
Because I don’t talk about fluff.
因为我没有什么水的东西
There’s a lot of substance to cover.
很多东西来讲
I also want to explore this through. Artificial intelligence, like DeepSeek, to see if it can help. Help me explain it. But the issue is DeepSeek can only provide some general outlines. He can elaborate more on certain aspects,
我现在我也想通过啊 这个人工智能是不是也那个这个来deep seek 帮我讲一讲 但是问题是 deep seek他只能讲一些大纲性质的东西 他更多的东西来讲
but he can't go into specifics.
他讲不出来
He tends to speak in more general terms.
他更多的东西他讲的是一种比较笼统的东西
So, he can't offer you specific, personalized guidance.
所以没有办法给你具体性的个性化的指导
That's why you can't rely solely on AI tools.
所以这个就是你不可能什么都依赖AI工具
Otherwise, you'll end up being too general.
否则你就做的会非常的英文讲generalization啊
Too mainstream.
做的非常的mainstream
Oh, very mainstream.
哎呀非常的主流
It doesn't differ much from the general perception.
跟大众认知差别也不大
You don't have any standout qualities.
你又没有一些一鸣惊人的地方
Gradually, you'll rely more on AI tools.
慢慢的你要依赖一些AI工具
In essence, you'll just become a conduit.
那么说白了你就变成了传声筒了
Why not just create a digital avatar then?
那你就干脆做一个数字分身形象不就完了
Why bother trying to be unique?
你干嘛还要做个性化的尝试呢
So, making a show and learning are two different things.
所以做节目跟长知识那是两码事情
Being a knowledge influencer, creating shows, or teaching courses is great.
做一个知识博主做节目做课也好啊
Or even selling courses.
还是卖课的啊
Selling books
卖书的
Selling courses
卖课
Selling products
卖书
Selling services
卖服务啊
You need to have your audience in mind
你首先心里就得有读者
Have your viewers in mind
有观众
What the audience loves to watch
观众爱看什么
What the audience truly cares about
观众真正关心什么
He would then take the time to watch it. He would then be willing to spend real money on it. These things are crucial. Keep the reader in mind. Keep the audience in mind. So you need to do this. You have to be like Chen Peisi.
他才会花时间去看 他才会花真金白银去买啊 这些东西是很重要的 心中要有读者 心中要有观众 所以你要做 你就必须要像陈佩斯那样
Like Zheng Yuanyuan.
像郑渊渊洁那样
These two masters.
这两位大师啊
A role model of our time
当代的楷模啊
Like writing Chuk Betta
像写舒克贝塔一样啊
How do you say that
像写这个怎么说
What was the name of that sketch again
那个那个那个那个那个小品叫什么来着
Right
对不对
It's like the sketch with Zhao Benshan and Zhu Shimao
那他跟车身佩斯跟朱时茂的小品一样
You need a lead and a supporting role
你就必须主角与配角
You must respect the rules of art
你必必须尊重艺术的规律
So you just read 150 pages a day
所以你光读一天读150页书
What's the point of reading 750 pages a day?
你一天读750页有什么用啊
Now we have AI,
有了AI了
everyone can read seven or eight hundred pages a day.
大家一天都可以读七八百页
There's no issue with that.
没有什么问题
Right?
对不对
What does this book talk about?
这个这本书里讲的什么
Highlight the key points for me.
你把核心的重点给我挑出来
You'll know right away.
马上你就能知道
But the joy of reading is something you have to experience yourself.
但是这个阅读的体验是你承受的快乐
So, a lot of things are counterintuitive.
所以很多的事情来讲
They defy common sense.
他就是反常识的
Many things go against human nature.
很多的事情他就是要反人性的
Often, you have to think deeply about them.
很多时候就是要琢磨啊
Why do I often enjoy reading business books?
为什么我经常爱看商业的书
Why do I prefer American authors?
为什么我爱看美国人的书啊
It’s not because I worship foreign things.
不是我因为我崇洋媚外
It’s that American writing tends to be more casual.
而是美国人写的东西呢比较随意啊
Unlike the more formal style in Chinese writing. Chapter One, Section One Chapter One, Section Two Chinese people are particularly afraid of losing face losing face Americans don't care Americans are really amusing very casual and spontaneous
不是像中国人写东西啊 第一章第一节 第一章第二节 中国人做事特别怕丢份啊 丢面子 老美不在乎 老美特别逗啊 特别随意随性
they write down whatever comes to mind
想到了什么东西就写到哪啊
driven by interest
以感兴趣为主
Chinese people are particularly afraid of writing.
中国人写东西特别怕
Oh!
哎呦
I can't let others look down on me.
我可别让别人瞧不起我啊
So, everything I do,
所以我其实所有的东西
is aimed at the common mistakes Chinese people make,
我的东西都是在冲着中国人常犯的错
targeting these weaknesses.
误的弱点去的啊
Some people say,
有人就说啊
sycophants think foreigners are great,
洋奴就说外国人好诶
but we are about learning from each other's strengths to make up for our weaknesses.
不是我们是取长补短
Learn from others' strengths
看到别人好的地方学过来
Their weaknesses
别人不好的东西
Why should we emulate them?
我们学它干嘛
Right?
对不对
They're all over the place
别人飘飘飘
Focusing on such things all day
整天那个这种东西
Why should we follow suit?
咱们学它干嘛
There's no need to learn from them
没有必要学
Agreed?
对不对
Our shortcomings are what hold us back.
我们不足的地方是阻碍我们前进的地方
For instance, our small-farmer mentality.
比如我们的小农意识
Being too concerned about what others think,
在意别人的看法啊
Not being ruthless enough when it comes to certain things,
有些东西来讲不够心狠啊
Caring too much about face.
好面子
These things slow us down.
这些东西是拖慢我们的脚步啊
Were our revolutionary martyrs like this?
我们的革命先烈是这样的人吗
No, they weren’t.
不是我们在整个的时候
Throughout the revolutionary process, Throughout the process of building The New China we often broke away from feudal traditions we broke down many established conventions we weren't so concerned with saving face
在整个革命的过程当中啊 在整个建设新中国的过程当中 很多的时候我们都是打破了封建传统的 我们都是打破了一些约定俗成的东西 不是在那么好面子啊
we broke some old rules
打破了一些啊成规啊
prejudices and the like
成见啊之类的啊
men and women were treated equally
男女都一样
that's how we achieved today's success
才有这样的今天
that's how we have today's bountiful harvest
才有今天的丰硕的果实
In today's new society
再有今天的新社会
So in many cases
所以很多时候来讲
We need to learn from different people
人就是要向不同的人学习
We should learn from everyone in the world
我们向世界所有人
Even if someone has a hundred flaws
哪怕别人100个缺点
As long as they have one strength
还有一个优点
We should still learn from them
咱们也把他学过来
Isn't that how we make it our own?
学过来不就是成自己的了嘛
Right?
对不对
Looking at the American PPT
看着老美的PPT
We should focus on our own stuff
咱们做咱们的东西啊
Right?
是不是
So even if he's not like that
所以他即使不是那样
We perceive him as such
咱们觉得他是那样
There's no harm in learning from it
也学过来也没什么关系啊
Isn't that so?
对不对
These flaws of ours
咱们的这些缺点
Do they cease to exist just because I don't mention them?
难道我不说它就不存在吗
Who should the fish head be directed at?
打鱼头该对着谁
Who is the main host?
谁是主陪
Who is the secondary host?
谁是副陪
Do you think these things are feudal dregs?
这些东西你觉得是封建糟粕
Or should they be something to learn with dedication?
还是应该呃用用心学习的东西啊
Sometimes, you know,
其实有的时候来讲呢
you have to learn the philosophy of gift-giving.
送礼的哲学你就得学
Because you still have to face this society, right?
因为这个社会你还要面对它啊
But a lot of social psychology,
但是很多一些社会心理学
individual psychology concepts, you should master if you need to. If you master what others don’t, aren’t you more capable? That’s how it is. So when I say what I do, do I need a script? What I do is actually in my heart.
个体心理学的东西 你该掌握就得掌握 你掌握了别人没掌握你不就厉害了吗 所以就是这么个东西 所以你说我做的东西 难道我需要有稿子吗 我做的东西其实它就在我心里边
What I do is because of the way I express myself.
我做的东西其实就是因为我这个人表达的东西
That’s just my habit.
他的习惯就是如此
It breaks some conventions.
打破了一些常规
It breaks some norms.
打破了一些东西
How loud should your voice be?
你说话的声音应该有多大
Your voice should be soothing enough to help others sleep.
你说话的声音应该能够以给别人助眠为主
So some things should have educational value,
所以一些东西易有教育意义
but they should also be entertaining,
但是同时要有娱乐性
and comforting.
同时要能安慰人
That’s the tone of my show.
这个东西才是我节目的调性
Everyone’s content is different.
所以每个人的东西是不一样的
Many people strive for correctness,
很多人追求的是正确啊
many people strive for rich content,
很多人追求的是知识内容丰富
but often,
但很多的时候来讲
I eat a bowl of instant noodles,
我吃个泡面
I wash my feet,
我洗个脚啊
before I sleep, I don’t want to hear anything too complex,
我睡觉之前我不想听这么复杂的
anything that might increase my anxiety.
会让我这个焦虑容易上升的东西
So you’ve read so many books,
所以你读了那么多书
you’ve read so many books,
你读了这么多书
your goal is to let others know you’ve read a lot of books,
你的目的就是为了让别人知道你读了很多书
so you’ve read a lot of books,
所以你读了很多书
you have to show off,
你就得装逼啊
you have to make others feel you’re extraordinary, but how do you make others feel extraordinary? Unless it’s someone who doesn’t know much, most people have knowledge, it’s just that everyone’s knowledge is categorized differently,
你就得让别人觉得你特别了不起啊 但是你怎么能让别人觉得特别了不起呢 那除非是知识不那什么的人 大部分人的知识都是有的 只是大家分门别类不一样
so you should make people feel happy first,
所以你就应该让大家首先感到开心
feel they’ve gained something,
有获得感
that’s very important.
这个东西很重要
So you need to break common knowledge,
所以你要打破常识啊
not just show off your knowledge,
而不是去卖弄知识
that’s why many people fail as knowledge bloggers,
所以这很多人做知识博主做不好
fail in commentary content,
做评论类的东西
the reason is this,
做不好的原因就在于此
because their content is either too broad or too specific,
因为他的东西要么就是泰国大中华
or too personalized,
要么就是太过个性化啊
waiting for others to react,
等着别人来哈
or they just follow others,
他要么就是跟着别人在一起
without any personal opinion,
没有任何的主观意见
turning it into a mere narrative of life,
就成了生活的讲述跟记录了
so what we do isn’t a VLOG,
所以像我们这种做不是VLOG
but commentary,
而是commentary的人
podcast content,
podcast的人
in short, you need to have a grasp of the overall social opinion,
说白了对社会的总体的意见要所有所掌握
but you also need to stand out a bit,
但是你又必须要高出来一点
follow the mainstream social trends,
必须要跟着社会的主流的思潮
yet not be exactly the same,
又完全不是那么一样
there must be some breakthroughs,
必须得有突破
at the same time, even if it’s critical content,
同时的时候虽然是批判类的东西
you need to speak in a normal tone,
但是你要本着这种比较正常的口吻去说
in a way that people can accept, not like it’s some kind of esoteric knowledge, so this is very important. Communication studies is specialized in communication studies, advertising studies is in advertising studies, journalism is in journalism,
能让人所接受 能让别人来讲啊 不是说那样像听天书一样 所以这个东西很重要 好传播学是专门的传播学 广告学是广告学
since they are different majors in universities,
新闻学是新生学
it tells you,
既然他是大学的不同专业
you can’t surpass them just by your imagination in a short time,
也就告诉你
then what’s the point of having television program producers?
不是你一朝一夕通过自己臆想就能超越的啊
What’s the point of having TV stations?
那要不要那广播电视节目编导干什么
What’s the point of having TV directors?
要电视台干什么
What's the role of a TV director?
要电视导演干什么
Then there's no such thing as directing studies
那就没有导演学
There's not much left of the discipline of broadcasting and anchoring in performance studies.
表演学没有什么播音与主持艺术了
There's nothing much.
没有什么啊
communication studies
传播学
Studying journalism doesn't cover new media research.
新闻学了没有什么新媒体研究了
Is that right?
对不对
So you've got it all down, then?
那这东西你就都掌握了就完了呗
So, if you want to become a knowledge influencer
所以你要想做一个知识博主
Is reading 150 pages a day enough?
是一天看150页书就行了吗
Isn't it true that swinging the sword 500 times a day helps you forget everything?
不是是一天练500下挥刀你就能忘却一切吗
It's not that you've been reading too many martial arts novels.
不是你是武侠小说看多了
So, if you want to do something, don't hesitate to ask for help.
所以想做什么东西就要不耻下问
It's about reaching out to others
就要向别人
Learn from those who do well
向那些做得好的人去学习
This is the way to progress in life.
这才是人生的进步之道